Register of the Robert L. Bartley papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert L. Bartley papers
1966-2003.
2005C56
Bartley, Robert L.
143 manuscript boxes. (48 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to political and economic conditions in the United States, international relations, international economic conditions, and the publication of the Wall Street Journal.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1937, October 12 Born, Marshall, Minnesota
1959 B.S., Iowa State University
1962 M.S., University of Wisconsin
1972-1978 Editorial page editor, Wall Street Journal
1979-2002 Editor, Wall Street Journal
1980 Awarded Pulitzer Prize for editorial writing
1992 Author, The Seven Fat Years: And How to Do It Again
2003, December 10 Died, New York City
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Robert L. Bartley document his thirty years successively as editorial page editor, and as overall editor, of the Wall Street Journal from 1972 to 2002. They include correspondence and other material detailing operations of the newspaper, and reportage and editorial commentary on financial, economic, political and military events, nationally and internationally. There is a large volume of material on financial and political scandals, especially relating to the Bank of Credit and Commerce International, the Watergate affair during the presidency of Richard M. Nixon, and the Whitewater and other affairs of the presidential administration of Bill Clinton. Other large bodies of material deal with supply-side economic policies, the Vietnamese War, the Iraq War, and biological and chemical warfare. The papers were acquired by the Hoover Institution from Edith Bartley in 2005.
This preliminary inventory reflects the present retention of the papers in folder arrangements made by Bartley. The folders have been grouped into series to accord as well as possible with the nature of the folder titles. Two caveats with respect to these series arrangements should be noted. The first is that the Speeches and Writings series does not contain all writings by Bartley, but merely those in folders with titles referring to a specific speech, conference participation, or article, or an aspect of the preparation of Bartley's book The Seven Fat Years. The Wall Street Journal File contains folders of aggregations of printed copies of articles and editorials from particular years of that publication, mostly unsigned, but many certainly written by Bartley. The Subject File consists of folders of diverse materials with titles indicating a specific topic. Frequently they include both articles or other writings by Bartley on that topic and materials by others on the same topic. The second caveat regarding retention of Bartley's own folder arrangement is that there is a certain incidence of filing, or misfiling, of extraneous material, related dubiously or not at all to the ostensible theme suggested by the folder title.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States Politics and government.; United States Foreign relations.; United States Economic conditions.; World politics.; Economics.; Journalism United States.; Journalists
Collection Contents
- Personal File, 1974-2002. (Folder 1-2.)
  So designated by Robert L. Bartley. Includes biographical data and photographs
  - General, including biographical data (Folder 1.)
  - Christmas cards
  - Correspondence concerning disposition of RLB papers
  - Financial records
  - Mementos (Folder 2.)
  - Photographs
  - Printed articles about RLB
- Appointment Books,1976-2003 (Folder 3-5.)
  - 1976 (Folder 3.)
  - 1979-1988
  - 1989-1996 (Folder 4.)
  - 1997-1999 (Folder 5.)
  - 2001-2003
- Notebook, undated (Folder 5.)
- Speeches and Writings, 1971-2003. (Folder 5-12.)
  Notes, drafts, typescripts, printed copies, correspondence, and research material. Some folders include extraneous material
  - "The Limits of the Press Corps in a Political/Technical Debate" (with Jude Wanniski), Conference on Expert Advice and Democratic Choice, Racine, Wisconsin, 1974 April 4-6 (Folder 5.)
  - Speech, Council on Foreign Relations meeting on South Africa, New York City, 1986 December 4
  - Speech, Forum Club, Houston, Texas, 1986 December 11
  - "Business Ethics and the Ethics Business," commencement address, Babson College, Babson Park, Massachusetts, 1987 May 16
  - The Great Crash of '29 and the Great Correction of '87 Compared panel discussion, Allied Social Science Association annual meeting, New York City, 1988 December 28
  - "Progress and Pessimism: Why Is Gloom Chic amid Peace and Prosperity?" speech, Town Hall luncheon, Los Angeles, California, 1989 August 16 (Folder 6.)
  - "Time to Shake our Hypochondria," Wall Street Journal, 1990 January 2
  - The Wealth of Nations: 1990 Conference, Edinburgh, Scotland, 1990 June 26-30
  - "The Great International Growth Slowdown," Wall Street Journal, 1990 July 10
  - Speech, Hudson Valley Forum, Poughkeepsie, New York, 1990 October 4
  - Speech, Pumpkin Papers Irregulars dinner, Washington, D.C., 1990 October 31
  - Bilderberg meetings, Baden-Baden, Germany, 1991 June 3-6
  - The Seven Fat Years: And How to Do It Again, 1992
    - Working materials, including drafts, outlines, correspondence and research material
    - Working materials (contd.) (Folder 7.)
    - Working materials (contd.) (Folder 8.)
    - Publicity materials
    - Reviews (Folder 9.)
    - Paperback edition. (Folder 10.)
      Drafts of introduction, epilogue and index, and other working materials
  - Senate Republican Conference weekend, Wilmington, Delaware, 1993 April 24-25 (Folder 11.)
  - "Reviving the U.S. Economy: A Blueprint," speech, Venture Investing 1993 Conference, San Francisco, California, 1993 June 22
  - "The Case for Optimism: The West Should Believe in Itself," Foreign Affairs, 1993 September-October
  - Speech on 1994 election results, unknown occasion, 1994
  - "A Time for Moralism," commencement address, Mayo Medical School, Rochester, Minnesota, 1995 May 20
  - "The Press and Elections, Issues and Scandals," Minow lecture, Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois, 1996 November 11
  - "Capitalism's Uncertain Trumpet," speech, Mont Pèlerin Society meeting, Washington, D.C., 1998 September 1
  - "The Future of Economic Freedom," lecture, Heritage Foundation regional meeting, Dearborn, Michigan, 2000 October 16
  - "Thirty Years of Progress, Mostly," speech, Forum Club, Houston, Texas, 2002 September 25 (Folder 12.)
  - Speech, occasion and exact date unknown, San Jose, California, 2002
  - "Backward on Understanding Profit," Charles Wolf lecture, RAND Corporation, Santa Monica, California, 2003 April 15
  - Speech on Iraq War, Rotary Club, place and exact date unknown, 2003
  - "The Beginning of the Journey" (re Clarence Barron), undated
  - Assorted articles in Wall Street Journal, various dates (1971-2002)
  - Assorted speeches, various dates (1981-1996)
- Wall Street Journal File, 1928-2003 (Folder 13-17.)
  Internal correspondence and memoranda, and printed articles from and about the Wall Street Journal
  - Internal memoranda and correspondence (Folder 13-14.)
  - Printed editorials and articles from the Wall Street Journal, mostly unsigned, including some by RLB (Folder 15.)
    - 1928-1989
    - 1990-1994 (Folder 16.)
    - 1995-2003 (Folder 17.)
  - Indexes to Wall Street Journal articles
  - Printed articles about the Wall Street Journal from other publications
- Correspondence, Chronological, 1970-2003 (Folder 18-24.)
  - 1970s, miscellaneous (Folder 18.)
  - 1978.
    Includes letters of congratulation upon promotion to editor of the Wall Street Journal
  - 1978 (contd.) (Folder 19.)
  - 1979
  - 1980.
    Includes letters of congratulation on Pulitzer Prize
  - 1980 (contd.) (Folder 20.)
  - 1982
  - 1983 (Folder 21.)
  - 1985
  - 1987-1988
  - 1989 (Folder 22.)
  - 1992
  - 1993-1995 (Folder 23.)
  - 1997-1998 (Folder 24.)
  - 2000s, miscellaneous
- Correspondence, Alphabetical, circa 1970-2003 (Folder 25-61.)
  - A-B (Folder 25.)
  - B (contd.) (Folder 26.)
  - B (contd.) (Folder 27.)
  - C
  - C (contd.) (Folder 28.)
  - C (contd.) (Folder 29.)
  - D
  - D (contd.) (Folder 30.)
  - D (contd.) (Folder 31.)
  - E
  - E (contd.) (Folder 32.)
  - F
  - F (contd.) (Folder 33.)
  - G (Folder 34.)
  - G (contd.) (Folder 35.)
  - H
  - H (contd.) (Folder 36.)
  - I
  - J-K (Folder 37.)
  - K (contd.) (Folder 38.)
  - L (Folder 39.)
  - M (Folder 40-43.)
  - N-O (Folder 44.)
  - O (contd.) (Folder 45.)
  - P
  - P (contd.) (Folder 46.)
  - P (contd.) (Folder 47.)
  - Q
  - R (Folder 48-50.)
  - S (Folder 51-55.)
  - T (Folder 56.)
  - T (contd.) (Folder 57.)
  - U-V
  - W (Folder 58-60.)
  - Y-Z (Folder 61.)
- Subject File, 1950-2003. (Folder 62-143.)
  Printed articles and other writings by RLB arranged topically; correspondence; printed matter and other research material by others. In a few cases entry is under name of author or correspondent rather than topic. Some folders include extraneous material
  - Accounting (Folder 62.)
  - Affirmative action
  - Ahlstrom, T. Robinson
  - American Bar Association
  - American Heritage Magazine
  - American Spectator
  - Amiel, Barbara
  - Andersen (Arthur) Company
  - Annie Get Your Gun (Musical) (Folder 63.)
  - Arabs
  - Armenians
  - Arms control.
    Includes material on missiles, lasers, nuclear strategy, and Strategic Arms Limitation Talks
  - Arms control (contd.) (Folder 64.)
  - Arms control (contd.) (Folder 65.)
  - Ashcroft, Michael
  - Asia
  - Asiaweek
  - Balance of payments
  - Balkans and Caucasus
  - Banca Nazionale del Lavoro (Folder 66.)
  - Bancroft family
  - Banfield, Edward C.
  - Bank of Credit and Commerce International.
    Includes material on Robert Altman, Clark Clifford and Ghaith Pharaon
  - Bank of Credit and Commerce International (contd.) (Folder 67-68.)
  - Bank of Credit and Commerce International (contd.) (Folder 69.)
  - Banking and bank regulation.
    Includes material by Robert Clarke
  - Barone, Michael
  - Barr Laboratories
  - Barron's Magazine
  - Bartley Institute (Proposed)
  - Bickel, Alexander M.
  - Biological and chemical warfare (Folder 70.)
    - General.
      Includes material on Sverdlovsk anthrax outbreak
    - Yellow Rain controversy (Southeast Asia) (Folder 71-74.)
    - Anthrax attack, 2001. (Folder 75.)
      Includes material re Steven Hatfill
  - Black Mischief controversy
  - Blumenthal, Sidney
  - Bork, Robert H. (Folder 76.)
  - Bosnia.
    Includes material by Albert Wohlstetter
  - Brady, Nicholas F.
  - Breast implants
  - Bretton Woods Agreement
  - Brock, Horace W.
  - Brown, Ron
  - Bruce-Briggs, B.
  - Bubbles (Finance)
  - Buckley, William F., Jr., and National Review. (Folder 77.)
    Includes material on antisemitism
  - Budget.
    Includes material on poverty programs
  - Burchett, Wilfred
  - Bush, George W.
    Includes material on religion, drunk driving, 2000 election campaign, and Bush Doctrine
  - Business cycles (Folder 78.)
  - Businessmen in the dock
  - Busing
  - CNBC (Television station)
  - Cambodia.
    Includes material on Ben Kiernan
  - Campaign finance
  - Capcom Financial Services
  - Capital formation (Folder 79.)
  - Capital gains
  - Capitalism
  - Casey, Paula J.
  - Center for Individual Rights
  - Central America
  - Chamberlain, John
  - Character assassination
  - Charts and statistics (Economics) (Folder 80.)
  - Child abuse allegations.
    Includes material on Wenatchee case
  - China.
    Includes material on intellectual property rights theft
  - Churchill School
  - Civil rights (Folder 81.)
  - Clark, Steve
  - Clash of civilizations thesis
  - Clinger, William
  - Clinton, Bill, and Clinton administration.
    Includes material on 1992 and 1996 election campaigns, and Clinton administration personnel and economic policy
  - Clinton, Hillary
  - Clinton administration scandals (Folder 82.)
    - General.
      Includes material on drugs, foreign influence, pardons, violence, White House staff, and impeachment
    - Foster, Vincent-Suicide (Folder 83-84.)
    - Sex scandals. (Folder 85.)
      Includes material on Gennifer Flowers, Paula Jones, Dick Morris, and Sally Perdue
    - Whitewater and other financial scandals.
      Includes material on the Whitewater Development Company, Beverly Enterprises, blind trusts, commodities trading, Dan Lasater, James McDougal, Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan Association, Dennis Patrick, Rose Law Firm, tax returns, Tyson Foods, and David Watkins
    - Whitewater and other financial scandals (contd.) (Folder 86-89.)
  - Cloning (Folder 90.)
  - Communications Workers of America vs. Beck
  - Conservatives
  - Conspiracies
  - Coolidge, Calvin
  - Corporate control and governance
  - Corporate scandals (Folder 91.)
  - Corporate taxes
  - Counterculture
  - Creative destruction
  - Credit demands
  - Crime
  - Crovitz, L. Gordon
  - Cultural crisis
  - Curran, Paul J.
  - Currency exchange rates (Folder 92.)
  - Daiwa Bank
  - Dalton, John H.
  - D'Amato, Alfonse
  - Dartmouth College
  - Daugherty, Harry M.
  - Deadline Club
  - Deficits and debt
  - Deflation
  - Democratic Party (Folder 93.)
  - Depressions
  - Derian, Patricia M.
  - Diana, Princess
  - Dinkins, David N.
  - Disgorgement (Finance)
  - Disinformation.
    Includes material on Libya
  - Ditchley Foundation
  - Dole, Bob, and Hollywood
  - Dow Jones Averages
  - Drew Investment Research and Management
  - Drexel Burnham Lambert Group
  - Drug pricing (Folder 94.)
  - Economy-General.
    Includes material on energy
  - Economy-General (contd.) (Folder 95.)
  - Economy-General (contd.) (Folder 96.)
  - Elections.
    Includes material on 1968, 1992 and 1996 elections
  - Elections (contd.) (Folder 97.)
  - Elitism
  - Energy.
    Includes material on Carter administration policy
  - Enron Corporation
  - Entrepreneurs (Folder 98.)
  - Environment
  - Epstein, Jason
  - Espionage
  - Establishment
  - Euro
  - Europe
  - Evans, Joseph E.
  - Exercise
  - Faludi, Susan
  - Falvey, Jack
  - Family values
  - Far Eastern Economic Review (Folder 99.)
  - Federal Reserve System
  - Feldstein, Martin
  - Ferraro, Geraldine
  - Filibuster (Folder 100.)
  - Financial Times
  - Flag burning
  - Flaps (Controversies)
  - Forbearance (Finance)
  - Foreign policy
  - Frank, Barney
  - Franklin Savings Association
  - Freeh, Louis
  - Gergen, David
  - Germany
  - Gingrich, Newt
  - Giuliani, Rudolph
  - Gold (Folder 101.)
  - Goodwin, Frank
  - Gore, Albert, and Viktor Chernomyrdin
  - Gould, Jay (Folder 102.)
  - Gross, Daniel
  - Growth and democracy
  - Guatemala
  - Haiti
  - Harriman family
  - Haynsworth, Clement
  - Health care (Folder 103.)
  - Helprin, Mark
  - Heymann, Philip B.
  - Hill, Anita, and Clarence Thomas
  - Holocaust and Holocaust Museum
  - Homosexuality (Folder 104.)
  - Hong Kong
  - Hubbell, Webster
  - Hunt, Al
  - Hustler Magazine
  - Hutchison, Kay Bailey, and Ronnie Earle
  - Ickes, Harold
  - Immigration
  - Income distribution
  - Income distribution (contd.) (Folder 105.)
  - Independent counsels
  - Index of Economic Freedom
  - Insider trading
  - Inslaw, Inc.
  - Internal Revenue Service (Folder 106.)
  - International Criminal Court
  - International Herald-Tribune
  - Intriago, Charles A.
  - Investment
  - Iowa State University
  - Iran-contra affair
  - Iraq and Iraq War
  - Iraq and Iraq War (contd.) (Folder 107.)
  - Iraq and Iraq War (contd.) (Folder 108.)
  - Israel.
    Includes material on right of return
  - Japan.
    Includes material on Shintaro Ishihara
  - Jeffrey, Christina (Folder 109.)
  - Jereski, Laura
  - Journalism.
    Includes material on journalists' politics
  - Junk bonds
  - Justice Department
  - Kaiser Permanente-Mental health coverage
  - Kaye, Scholer, Fierman, Hays and Handler (Law firm)
  - Kennedy, Edward M.-Chappaquiddick incident
  - Kennedy, John F. (Folder 110.)
    Includes material on Judith Exner and Vietnam policy
  - Kilgore, Bernard
  - Kinsley, Michael
  - Kissinger, Henry
  - Korea, North
  - Kosovo
  - Kuttner, Robert
  - Lake, Anthony
  - Lawson, Nigel
  - League of Nations
  - Lee, Wen Ho
  - Left rhetoric
  - Leveraged takeovers
  - Levy, Paul
  - Lipsky, Seth (Folder 111.)
  - Long-term capital
  - Loral Space Systems
  - McCarthyism
  - McDonough, William J.
  - McGovern, George
  - Maddison, Angus
  - Malaysia
  - Maltby, Barbara
  - Media
  - Medicare.
    Includes material on Federal Employees Health Benefits Plan
  - Medicine and medical issues (Folder 112.)
  - Mexico
  - Mexico (contd.) (Folder 113.)
  - Mexico (contd.) (Folder 114.)
  - Mikva, Abner
  - Milken, Michael
  - Millennium (2000) (Folder 115.)
  - Money and monetary policy
  - Moynihan, Daniel P.
  - Mundell, Robert A.
  - Mundell, Robert A. (contd.) (Folder 116.)
  - Murray, Charles
  - National Conference of Editorial Writers
  - National Rifle Association.
    Includes material on George W. Bush
  - National security.
    Directive by Harry S. Truman
  - New era (Post 9-11)
  - New York (State) (Folder 117.)
  - New York City
  - New York Times
  - New York University.
    Includes material on its science program
  - Nineteen sixties
  - Nixon, Richard M. (Folder 118.)
    Includes material on civil rights policy, San Clemente residence, and presidential finances
  - Nobel Prizes (Folder 119.)
  - Non-lethal weapons
  - Oil.
    Includes material on the 1973 embargo and the Hubbert curve
  - Oklahoma City bombing
  - Olayan, Suliman S.
  - Olympic games
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development. (Folder 120.)
    Includes material on tax havens
  - Ossuary (Purported biblical archeological artifact)
  - Outward Bound program
  - Palestine Liberation Organization
  - Paramount Communications
  - Pataki, George
  - Pearl Harbor attack
  - Pearson, Hugh
  - People for the American Way
  - Pepper and Salt (Cartoon)
  - Perjury (Folder 121.)
  - Perot, Ross.
    Includes material on economic program
  - Points of Light Initiative
  - Politics-General
  - Pollard, Jonathan
  - Postal Service
  - Powell, Colin
  - Poynter, Nelson
  - Pre-Reagan era
  - Presidents, great and small
  - Press. (Folder 122.)
    Includes material on objectivity
  - Prisons
  - Pritchett, Kevin
  - Productivity (Folder 123.)
  - The Progressive
  - Prudential Insurance Company-Robert Fiske lawsuit
  - Puerto Rico
  - Pulitzer Prizes
  - Purchasing power parity.
    Includes material by Ronald I. McKinnon
  - Quayle, Dan (Folder 124.)
  - Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act
  - Reagan, Ronald
  - Recall elections
  - Regulation Q (Federal Reserve System)
  - Religion
  - Reno, Janet
  - Rent control
  - Republican Contract with America (Folder 125.)
  - Rescorla, Rick, and 9/11
  - Rich, Marc
  - Ridge, Tom
  - Right to petition
  - Roach, Stephen S.
  - Roberts, Paul Craig
  - Robertson, Pat
  - Rostenkowski, Daniel
  - Rule of law
  - Rumsfeld, Donald
  - Russia and Soviet Union.
    Includes material on Marxism, Russian empire, and Russian Mafia
  - Russia and Soviet Union (contd.) (Folder 126.)
  - Rwanda
  - Ryan, Jack
  - Santorum, Rick
  - Saudi Arabia
  - Savings and loan association crisis
  - Scandals, Miscellaneous
  - Scientology.
    Includes material on Keith Henson
  - Scientology (contd.) (Folder 127.)
  - Secular humanism
  - Securities fraud prosecutions.
    Includes material on Robert M. Morgenthau
  - Shaw, David
  - Shesol, Jeff
  - Simpson, O. J.
  - Singapore.
    Includes material on Lee Kuan Yew
  - Singapore (contd.) (Folder 128.)
  - Singapore (contd.) (Folder 129.)
  - Smith, Adam
  - Social Security.
    Includes material on Daniel P. Moynihan
  - Somalia
  - Southeast Banking Corporation
  - Space shuttle
  - State Department
  - State of the union
  - Stephens Inc. (Folder 130.)
  - Stimulus packages
  - Stock option accounting
  - Stockman, David
  - Strauss, Leo
  - Student unrest
  - Supply-side economics (Folder 131.)
  - Switzerland
  - Syria
  - Systematics, Inc.
  - Taste
  - Taxes. (Folder 132.)
    Includes material on credits, deficits, enforcement, international aspects, and spending
  - Teamsters-Philadelphia
  - Term limits (Folder 133.)
  - Terrorism
  - Thanksgiving
  - Thomas, Michael M.
  - Timerman, Jacobo
  - Tobacco fee
  - Tribunals
  - Turkey
  - Turkey (contd.) (Folder 134.)
  - Tuttle, Alexandra
  - Unabomber
  - Uncaused causes
  - United Nations.
    Includes material on Boutros Boutros-Ghali
  - Vanity Fair
  - Vassar College (Folder 135.)
  - Veto
  - Vietnam.
    Includes material on Hmong refugees and Barry Wain
  - Vietnamese War.
    Includes material on air war, amnesty, Cambodian aspects, Henry Kissinger, Ngo Dinh Diem, Richard M. Nixon, Paris peace agreement, prisoners of war, and Thich Tri Quang
  - Vietnamese War (contd.) (Folder 136-138.)
  - Vietnamese War (contd.) (Folder 139.)
  - Wage-price controls
  - Wagner, Bernard M.
  - Wanniski, Jude
  - War and war powers.
    Includes material on the American Civil War, World War II, and Iraq War
  - War and war powers (contd.) (Folder 140.)
  - Ward Industries
  - Washington Post
  - Watergate affair.
    Includes material on impeachment
  - Watergate affair (contd.) (Folder 141.)
  - Weather (Folder 142.)
  - Whip Inflation Now policy (Nixon and Ford administrations)
  - Wilson, James Q.
  - Wohlstetter, Albert.
    Includes material on Persian Gulf War
  - Wolfowitz, Paul
  - World War II
  - Worthen Banking Corporation
  - Yale University (Folder 143.)
  - Miscellany.
    Includes folders with material on diverse topics